Welcome back to APUSH in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So, this Cold War is intense in
many ways, but it is not over by a long
shot, and it's time to talk about one of
its biggest conflicts, which was the
Vietnam War. So, let's look at a map of
Southeast Asia. After defeating France,
Vietnam split into the communist north
under Ho Chi Minh and the non-communist
South Vietnam. And almost immediately,
the two sides go to war. The US's
thinking here will be the domino theory,
which was the belief that if Vietnam
fell to communism, other Southeast Asian
countries would follow. So, the US
essentially just wanted to contain
communism spread. So, it starts off
pretty simple. The US will start by
sending money and advisers, but then the
Gulf of Tonkin incident happens, where
two US boats are attacked by North
Vietnam. Now, in retrospect, this
incident was very exaggerated, and parts
of it were likely made up, but it didn't
really matter because it caused the
president of the time, Lyndon B.
Johnson, to use the incident to justify
full military involvement in Vietnam by
the US. And so, the US will officially
enter Vietnam. It will implement a full
military draft and send hundreds of
thousands of untrained young boys to
fight, and it will quickly become a
full-on war. Once the US is fully
involved in Vietnam, the war quickly
becomes a nightmare because it isn't a
traditional fight. Communist soldiers
who supported the north, but fought in
the south, were called the Viet Cong,
and they do not operate like regular
soldiers. Instead, they move within
South Vietnam. Using the Ho Chi Minh
Trail for supplies, they blend in with
civilians and rely on ambushes, booby
traps, and tunnel systems. This makes it
incredibly difficult for millions of US
soldiers to tell who the enemy is. So,
then you see a few things happen. The
Tet Offensive happens in Vietnam, where
North Vietnamese soldiers launch a
massive series of surprise attacks on
the south, and then the Pentagon Papers
get released, showing that US leaders
had been secretly expanding and
misrepresenting the war, while lying to
the public saying that things were under
control. And finally, the My Lai
Massacre happens, where US soldiers
killed hundreds of unarmed Vietnamese
civilians. All of these combined
together caused the US public to most
openly despise this war. The result here
is college protests, widespread draft
resistance, and cultural divide. This
will lead to the War Powers Act, which
basically said that the president can't
just drag the US into war without
Congress. And finally, when Nixon
becomes president, he begins pulling US
soldiers out of Vietnam until finally,
in 1975, the US officially exits the
war. North Vietnam wins, and Vietnam
becomes communist. How about that? For
once in history, the US actually loses.
On the screen now are AP-style questions
for this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.